<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Protestant conformist, or, A plea for moderation contained in a letter from one conforming minister to another : and his answer to it.</title>
            <author>N. Y.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D68</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4499</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12790457</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12790457</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93934</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93934)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 378:5, 451:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Protestant conformist, or, A plea for moderation contained in a letter from one conforming minister to another : and his answer to it.</title>
                  <author>N. Y.</author>
                  <author>N. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letter is dated and signed "Septemb. 13, 1679. N.Y." and the reply "Septemb. 22, 1679. N.D."</note>
                  <note>Print show-through makes filmed copy difficult to read.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93934:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Proteſtant Conformiſt: OR, A PLEA FOR MODERATION, Contained in a LETTER FROM One Conforming MINISTER to another: and His ANSWER to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst,</hi> at the
<hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> near
<hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi> M.DC.LXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:93934:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93934:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear and Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF you knew how ſeverely I charge my ſelf with my remiſneſs in anſwering your laſt, you would more readily pardon me; and when I conſider your candor and moderation, I cannot (upon my involuntary tranſgreſſions) deſpair of your Clemency: for amongſt all thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Qualities that adorn you, and whereby you adorn the Goſpel, and our Function, That vertue or rather grace of Moderation has graven the moſt deep and indelible characters of endearedneſs upon me; and though your worth has placed you above contempt, and not left ſo bright a Taper under a Buſhel, yet I could even wiſh for the ſakes of others, that you were poſted in a more conſpicuous Eminency, that (in this ſenſe alſo) <hi>your Moderation might be known unto all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now that I have ſo grateful a Theme, I cannot ſo eaſily take leave of it, but that I muſt beg your pardon if (waving till the next opportunity ſome other things I ſhould have mentioned to you) I go on to bemoan the too evident and epidemick want of this Chriſtian vertue amongſt thoſe of us that juſtly pretend to the beſt form of Chriſtianity, as moſt ſuitable to the revealed will of God, and the Pattern of the moſt pure and Primitive times: For as to our adverſaries ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting of Novelty upon us, it has been ſo fully and clearly redargued, that I need not meddle with it. That I would be at, is, To convince my Brethren, the Sons of my Mother, of the abſolute neceſſity and ſeaſonableneſs of this Grace of Moderation, as the <hi>Cauſa ſine qua non</hi> of the ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and continuance of our Reformed Religion. I tell you no news, becauſe you have ſometimes obſerved it to me, That our <hi>Roman</hi> Adverſaries (who like their Pagan Predeceſſors will <hi>per fas aut nefas</hi> be maſters of the World) can manage any Game, Play on any Inſtrument, work with all Tools, tranſcend <hi>Proteus</hi> in change of ſhapes, have while we ſlept (with the aſſiſtance of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) ſown Tares in our Field, which now they ſo carefully water and cheriſh that they expect a plentiful Harveſt, I mean thoſe Diſſentions and Animoſities amongſt Proteſtants, and to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of bitterneſs, clamour, and reviling each other, that they hope it ſhall not end there, but that (their other great Engines having lately miſcarried) they may ſit ſtill a while and ſee us with delight carrying on their work for them how well do they know that a Kingdom or Church divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand? And though they need not to be Diſciples to the <hi>Florentine</hi> (for <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Conclave has far out-done him yet that ſhort <hi>Recipe,</hi> of
<hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> they find ſuch a never-failing Medicine, as they have thereby Horſe-leach'd a great deal of the beſt blood in
<hi>Europe.</hi> What Quacks are theſe in moſt Princes Courts? Who knows not what their Reſidence at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and their hanging there (more cloſe than Pendants) at that soft Head of that Spread (or rather ſhatter'd) Eagle, has done? how have they drawn him to make Enemies of good Subjects in
<hi>Hungary,</hi> becauſe Proteſtants? and by his inexorable cruelty to them for Religions ſake, to pull down with his own hands the Ramparts of
<hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> by forcing thoſe who heretofore were the
<hi>Remora</hi> in the <hi>Creſcents</hi> Progreſs Weſtward, to take Protection under the growing but more pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Turk?</hi> How theſe Earwigs ſwarm'd about <hi>Madrid</hi> and the <hi>Eſcurial</hi> whilſt there was any likelihood of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Families doing their work, and how upon the decline of that they have crawld about the <hi>Flower de Lis,</hi> (for theſe Summer-Inſects do adore Eaſtward, and have no Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty but the riſing-Sun); how they (the moſt ſedulous ſervants in
<hi>Vulcan</hi>'s ſhop) have plied their Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows at the <hi>Louvre,</hi> till their inflations have ſo ſwoln that already great-enough mind, that the beſt part of <hi>Europe</hi> will hardly hold it, and moſt Nations of it have ſmarted for preſuming by juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to interrupt his growing Glory? and how they have horn-bound for ſeveral years paſt the
<hi>Bavarian</hi> Duke, though never without a conſiderable Army, from aſſiſting his Neighbour Princes againſt the <hi>Galick</hi> Invaſions, they are ſtrangers to the Affairs of <hi>Europe</hi> that know not.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Paris</hi> Cabal can tell us, that that fine Texture of ſetting the Northern Princes of the Reformed Religion by the ears, was firſt ſpun in <hi>Loyola</hi>'s <hi>Parlour,</hi> though wrought up by
<hi>Pariſian</hi> Statiſts. I might trace the <hi>Veſtigia</hi> of theſe Helliſh blood-hounds through many Countries, till I ſhould loſe my ſelf and weary you; but refer you to Mr. <hi>Wadſworth</hi>'s Memoirs (which you have ſeen e're this) for ſome of their Projects in
<hi>Germany,</hi> wherein they eſteemed it a Maſter-piece ſo to order the matter, as to ſet a <hi>Calviniſt</hi> Prince againſt a
<hi>Lutheran,</hi> and ſo e <hi>contra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, <hi>Sir,</hi> having been long enough a Tranſmarine Obſerver, (and conſidering the caſe laſt mentioned makes me a good Errant home) I conclude it more than high time to return, for I find they are arrived before me: And how willingly would I lend my Optick Glaſſes to thouſands of Proteſtants (otherwiſe I hope loyal and well qualified) whoſe will or uncharitable humour ſo hanging in their light, hinders them from ſeeing how buſie at work theſe Scorpions are amongſt us: we need not to be ſent back to 88, or the fifth of <hi>Novemb.</hi> Anno 1605. Theſe Hiſtories are believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all good Proteſtants, though
<hi>Apocryphal</hi> to them who would act the ſame over again; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if we will take their own words <hi>ex poſt facto,</hi> they were never guilty of Treaſons, bloody <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93934:3"/>Conſpiracies and Tragedies, no not they. Oh what omnipotent Prieſts have they! that can, as they make a god of Bread, make Treaſon and Guilt after a ſhrift to loſe their nature and the moſt enormous Traitors like Children unborn, innocent of all ſins but original, and that but ſome of them!</p>
            <p>The worſt on't is, that not only they have the Braſs to impoſe on the World, but that ſome of our ſelves have the facility (I dare not call it charity) to take theſe counter feits for good coyn, and forſooth out of animoſity to other Proteſtants to believe the
<hi>Papiſts</hi> innocent. I defie the beſt Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Soldier to help forward the Popiſh Deſign more effectually than we ſhould do, were we but all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this mind; for my part, far be it from me to palliate or extenuate Treaſons or Rebellions under the Cloak of Religion and Reformation, for theſe inſtead of ſetting a better gloſs fix a deeper ſtain, or more inexpiable guilt and horrid brand upon the Action and Actors; yet wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all is done you are ſatisfied as well as I that in the beginnings of our late wretched Wars one might ſay of many of the other Party as of thoſe that went with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> they went in the ſimplicity of their heart, and they knew not any thing; to my knowledg many of them did as much as poſſible condole the horrid conſequences of that War, and did believe as you and I alſo did, that the Finger of <hi>Joab</hi> had an unſeen motion in thoſe affairs, though perſonally and viſibly acted by men whoſe after climbing to the ſeat of Government ſhew'd what was before in their hearts; as he ſees little in the world that knows not that the ſelf-ſame Deſign may not be endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured and driven on by men of contrary Principles, and for contrary ends. I had not inſiſted on this ſo well known already to you, but that I hear with ſome grief our young Levites (who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaw nor ſuffered what we did) Hectoring at that rate againſt ſome innocent Proteſtants, and which my Ink it ſeems ſhould bluſh to recite, declaring that they would rather cloſe with the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> than admit of compoſure with Diſſenting Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>It is an ordinary Obſervation, That a quarrel amongſt neareſt Relations is often moſt grievous; but when one of ſuch for meer revenge will unite himſelf to the mortal enemy of both, who will not affirm him void of not only grace but good nature! Oh degenerate Age!</p>
            <p>Where is that Evangelical peace and love, our Saviours bleſſed Legacy! where's that ſervent charity! is it turned into burning hatred? Where's that Moderation we ſhould ſhew unto all men! is it degenerated into the moſt inexorable rancor? That ſheep ſhould ſtray and ſometimes encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one another in the abſence of the wolf is not ſtrange; but when the wolves come, they at leaſt unite, and not having power to reſiſt, flie together. That theſe wolves of <hi>Romulus</hi> abound a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, all now that are not already guld by them. But to elude the care of our vigilant Shepherds, theſe Monſters worſe than that which
<hi>Hercules</hi> wreſtled with, have dwindled the Wolf into a Fox, and to avoid ſuſpicion have cunningly cover'd that too with Lambs wool, that it requires much circumſpection to diſcover them.</p>
            <p>He that hath read the Legend of their Clowniſh St.
<hi>Francis,</hi> and the ſtory of the <hi>Illuminati,</hi> will eaſily believe who are the Fathers of our Quaking Sect, though themſelves poſſibly know not; and it is too eviden that they have ſcrewed themſelves, and transſuſed their Influences into all the ſeveral Perſwaſions amongſt us, none excepted. And as they take the cawls of our ſheep in the fields for compounding their Fire balls to burn our Cities, ſo in compenſation they inſtill wilder fire under the notion of zeal, (an excellent grace of it ſelf, but miſguided, of moſt diſmal effects) into the ſheep of the great Shepherd, to the renewing of the complaint, <hi>Homo homini Lupus.</hi> And without controverſie, if they find their expected ſucceſs, theſe <hi>Flambeaus</hi> will much more prompt their work, than thoſe they beſtowed ſo freely towards the deſtroying of our Mother-city in 66.</p>
            <p>And that we may better conjecture what they are doing elſewhere, I ſhall give you a skant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of what we obſerved in my own Pariſh, though too late taken notice of, elſe probably the world might have known the perſons as well as the deſign: Two Gentlemen pretty well accoutred took up a Lodging together, they ſeem'd no contemptible perſons, nor wanted moneys, they both wore Perukes, and which made ſome the more ſuſpicious of them) had conſiderable variety, and differing much in colour, yet ſeldom made uſe of their Flaxen ones in Town, but as one of the Maids of the houſe obſerved, he that rode abroad ofteneſt took one of that ſort in his Coat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocket; the Neighbourhood begun to imagine them Highway-men, but one of them ſeldom riding abroad during their ſix Months ſtay here, and their orderly <hi>Decorum</hi> and converſe, begot a better opinion of them; one was obſerved to go frequently to the meetings of Diſſenters, and there behave himſelf as ſeriouſly as any of them; the other when he was not out of Town (ſot he commonly ordered his Journeys on Friday or Saturday, and returned on Monday) would moſtly come to the Pariſh-Church, and to any ones ſight demean himſelf very devoutly: He would or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e could find opportunity be in the company of good Conſormiſts, and if none elſe hapned to ſpeak of Church-affairs he would break the Ice, and moſtly begin with magnifying the Church of <hi>England</hi> as the beſt conſtituted in the world; and after a large Harangue (for he could ſpeak with a Grace) would bemoan the Diviſions in it, and conclude with the neceſſity of extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating all Diſſenters root and branch; for elſe, ſays he, thoſe
<hi>Samaritans</hi> will never reſt till they have yazed it to the very ground. This was his ordinary Theme, though with ſome variation of words, till one time a good Neighbour of mine zeplied upon him: <hi>Sir,</hi> 'Tis a true ſaying, it's ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to give than take Counſel; how do you practiſe what you adviſe to, while it appears your <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93934:3"/>Comerade your boſom-friend is one that frequents Conventicles, and is daily in the company of ſuch, cannot you either win him or diſcard him? Oh,
<hi>Sir,</hi> ſays he, I muſt tell you he is my inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate friend of a long ſtanding, and I can digeſt his converſation in all things but that, which for good reaſons I do a little indulge, for by him I have in this, as well as other places where we have reſided (my Neighbour thought this ſlipt undeſignedly from him) the advantage of knowing their ſecret diſcourſes and machinations againſt the Church, and thereby the means of juſtly inciting the zeal of ſuch good men as you againſt this generation of Vipers. This ſtirred up the choler of an honeſt Mechanick that had quietly liſtened all this while, that he broke ſilence thus: For my part I neither like you nor your friend; and it's well if you be not brethren in evil, or like
<hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes that you turn tails to do miſchief; 'tis well known in the Town that I go conſtantly to Church, and yet (I hope here's no Informers here) I often hear an honeſt Miniſter preach elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and I hope my care of being inſtructed for another world will neither offend the Juſtices, nor the Parſon. If I had heard any preach ſedition, I would have quickly (as it is my duty) have acquainted the Magiſtrates with it. But I tell you, (and then he ſpoke with more impatience I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard a man in my life talk ſo diſloyally as your companion, ſo that I have carefully avoided his company of late; and he has ſo bedawbed the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> and rendered the fears of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranical uſage from them ſo formidable, and that they would uſe us worſe than <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his deſign was to turn us <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and however moſt of the people that have any degree of Prudence and ſobriety could wiſh him with his fellows in <hi>Newgate,</hi> yet there's one or two that I fear he has perverted, and it may be we ſhall hear more of him, or you elſewhere; for I heard this very day of one of your haunts not far from this place.</p>
            <p>This ſmart Reply of an inconſiderable man, was rebuked by ſome as too malepert to a ſtranger of ſeeming quality; but approved by others, as likely to have in it as much of Truth as he wanted of Patience. The Gentleman concerned, though he could not keep his colour from changing, yet keeping his countenance as well as he could; ſaid, Gentlemen, I have ſojourned now about ſix Months amongſt you, and I hope none has found incivility from me, neither have I till now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred any rudeneſs from any perſon, to the honour of your Town I ſpeak; and now that this mean perſon whoſe imployment is about the feet, ſhould thus flee in my face, and to expreſs his cauſeleſs pique againſt me, turn all his Tools into Awls to gore that Reputation my fair deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has obtained amongſt you, 'tis ſomewhat grievous; but when you have known me as long as him, you will know how-little I have deſerved to be thus accoſted.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Company broke up, ſome of whom came and related the whole to me; my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was that they ſhould acquaint the Magiſtrates, and take a Conſtable with ſome aſſiſtance to ſearch their Chamber, which (the day being far ſpent) they reſolved to do next morning. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many people in the Town were up, theſe hopeful Chickens had taken the wing; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all our care by Meſſengers and Letters, where we imagined they had haunted, we could meet with no further ſatisfaction than that our Town was well quit of them; and that by their deſigned evil, this good is arrived to us, that my Pariſhioners of all ſorts live in more love and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity than heretofore: thoſe of both parties that have been moſt enflamed by theſe <hi>Boutefeus</hi> to the greateſt height of animoſity, being moſt aſhamed that they ſhould have been over-acted by thoſe
<hi>Roman</hi> Engines. Some of the Servants of that Inn where they Lodged, have ſince (which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not in time) told ſeveral ſtories of having ſeen Beads and other Trinkets too tedious now to recite. The ſtory and deſign are plain enough, they need no Comment.</p>
            <p>Some that are backward to believe any thing againſt ſuch men, will be ready to ſay, <hi>Quorſum haes perditio,</hi> would they take ſuch care and pains to play at ſuch ſmall games? With the leave of ſuch incredulous, this is no ſmall game; for as I hinted before, this is their chief though after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game, and as like to do their Jobb for them as any enterprize they ever undertook.</p>
            <p>For my own particular I ſhall, by Gods aſſiſtance, keep my ſtation, and I hope rather grow than decline in that grace of Moderation I ſo much priſe and praiſe in you; and if ſome of our Tribe will go on to Lord it over Gods Heritage, inſtead of being Enſamples to their Flock, or learning of Chriſt to be meek and lowly in ſpirit: If others will be ſmiting their fellow ſervants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall make it my Prayers and conſtant endeavour that when my Lord and Maſter comes he may not find me ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Dear Sir, I was not ſo confident of any worth in what I could obſerve or relate, but that I was about to caution you to avoid expoſing it; but ſith that might ſtruſtrate the end for which I have given you this trouble, I leave it to your own Prudence to communicate as you think fit. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your unworthy Fellow-ſervant, N. Y.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Septemb.</hi> 13. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93934:4"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to the former LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough your affections do blind your judgment, to think better of me than I deſerve, yet I hope you will always find me a true lover and practicer of that moderation, which (is ſo much my duty, and which) you ſo much adore. I am very well contented with the Station in which God hath ſet me; High places will not ſuit with ſuch weak heads as mine: I am not ſorry I am out of that temptation, leſt a Vertigo ſhould take me, and make me fall down the precipice which lyes before me. I cordially approve of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſign of your ingenious Letter, and have taken the liberty (which you did not deny me) to putliſh it, with my own approbation of it.</p>
            <p>He muſt wilfully ſhut his eyes, that will not ſee how buſie the Jeſuits and Romiſh Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries are, both at home and abroad, to promote their grand deſign; and how all things are lawful with them, that are uſeful to promote their Catholick Cauſe: Their late deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate helliſh Plot againſt the perſon of a Prince ſo full of clemency towards them, and againſt our Civil and Religious Liberties, as Engliſh men and Proteſtants; their devilliſh deſigns to deſtroy our perſons, and to enſlave our conſciences and poſterities, may juſtly raiſe our juſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt them; and put us upon ſtudy and endeavours, to beget a right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between all true Proteſtants, and not to narrow, or weaken the intereſt of our Church, by our her childiſh contentions and diviſions; but to unite and ſtrengthen it what we can, againſt the common enemy that is undermining of it. Alas! our young raw heads grow giddy, and, I fear, gaze ſo much at the golden Cup, that they will be eaſily tempted to drink of the poiſonous abominations contained in it. Nothing is more obvious to common obſervation, than the Jeſuits transforming themſelves into all ſhapes, and mingling themſelves with all parties, to heat and heighten mens ſpirits, and to ſoment and widen differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween true Proteſtants: And as no party can excuſe or clear themſelves from having been abuſed by them, ſo all had need to be watchful leſt they give advantage and encouragement to them. It's pleaſant to read the ſtory acted in your Pariſh, and the wiſe improvement and advantage that both you and your pariſhoners make of it. I heartily pray, that both you and I may obtain mercy from God, to be faithful and diligent in our work, That whilſt others are found eating and drinking with the drunken,
<hi>and ſmiting their fellow ſervants;</hi> we may be like <hi>that faithful and wiſe Steward, whom his Lord will make ruler over his houſhold, to give them their portion of meat in due ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have two of the moſt precious, excellent things in the world committed to our truſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The glorious Goſpel of the bleſſed God, and the precious ſouls of men, and if we did more ſeriouſly mind the diſcharge of our truſt, we ſhould find little heart or leaſure to quarrel with others about trifles. I cannot but bewail the unſeaſoanble heats of our younger fry, whoſe bitter zeal runs out againſt perſons and things which they do not underſtand. How nauſeous is it to ſober ears, to hear a Hectoring youngſter let fly at <hi>Jack Calvin,</hi> whom our Reverend Prelates and Doctors of the Church (who were better Champions for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than theſe Novices are like to make) did never mention without reverence and reſpect; as is evident to any verſed in the Writings of A. Bp. <hi>Whitgift,</hi> Bp.
<hi>Andrews,</hi> Bp. <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Willet, &amp;c?</hi> Though perhaps it's but a man of Straw of their own making, that theſe valiant Champions are crowing over: And to hear theſe inveigh againſt our firſt and moſt zealous Reformers, for ſome different apprehenſions, or expreſſions, about ſome abſtruſer and darker points, which (themſelves have never ſtudied nor underſtood) and the Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſeem ſo much to favour, is loathſom to ſober minds; and begets an opinion in thoſe that have any prejudice againſt, or are diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that we are returning again to <hi>Rome,</hi> and enemies to the Reformation they firſt promoted. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the putting all diſſenters in the ſame rank, and beſpattering them with the names of Schiſmaticks, Factious, and Seditious (though many of them do not break communion with us) to me ſeems very harſh and unreaſonable, if not unjuſt. It's well known to the world, there be many learned, ſober, godly men amongſt them (ſome whereof, you and I have the happineſs of a proſitable acquaintance, and ſweet converſation with) who though they be not ſatisfied to do ſome things the Law requires, (and which our Church might well ſpare, if our Rulers ſaw meet to diſpenſe with them) that otherwiſe are as true to, and ſome of them as zealous, able Champions for the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as any of our ſelves. This fooliſh di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding humour, helps to widen, and keep open the difference between true Proteſtants; and mens diſtances from, and unacquaintedneſs with each other, makes them to look upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Hobgoblins, and frightful apparitions; whereas a more familiar acquaintance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93934:4"/>together, would let men ſee that they are not ſuch Bugbears and monſters, as ſome fiery Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots on both ſides repreſent them to be. When I came firſt to this place, my Predeceſſor (who was a <hi>Don Furioſo</hi> againſt Diſſenters, and looked upon himſelf thereby as better qualified for the Preferment which he obtained) told me I muſt beware of ſuch perſons in my Pariſh that were dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, factious, and turbulent fellows; and of ſuch a Miniſter (who preached amongſt them) as a peſtilent fellow, and a mover of ſedition. But upon a little trial and obſervation, I found they were the moſt ſerious diligent Auditors I had; and upon a further enquiry after them, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with them, I perceived they were ſuch as lived moſt conſcientiouſly in the practice of the great unqueſtionable duties of Chriſtianity in all my Pariſh. I ſaw none ſo charitably diſpoſed upon any good occaſion; none more juſt in their dealings, none more ready or willing to give me my juſt dues; none more peaceable among their neighbours, ſtriving to prevent or compoſe differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; none more careful to ſanctifie the Sabbath, to inſtruct their Children and Servants; and to pray in their Families, making conſcience both of firſt and ſecond Table Duties; and in one word, ready to every good work. I wiſh I could ſay ſo of all thoſe that glory to be ſtiled <hi>true Sons of the Church of England;</hi> and which he commended to me as ſuch, whoſe zeal runs out mainly, if not only for Rites and Ceremonies, and will cry devoutly on the Lords day with us in the publick Liturgy, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us miſerable ſinners;</hi> and yet live all the week without any open or ſolemn acknowledgment of God in their Families. And as for the Miniſter he gave ſuch a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of, I found him an holy, learned, modeſt, ſelf-denying man, who ſeems to have no deſign but to get to Heaven himſelf, and to get as many thither with him as poſſibly he can. He is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently my Auditor, and I have much pleaſing converſation with him. It's the grief of my ſoul that we cannot take ſuch men into our Pulpits (without offence), who if they might but have that liberty, would never run into corners as we now drive them. And this Gentleman (to ſhun all occaſions of offence) never Preaches in the time of our publick Service, but the people come conſtantly to hear me, and when we have done, he Preaches to them, and many others go to hear him, which I am not offended at, but rather bleſs God for ſuch an helper in my work.</p>
            <p>And truly we may talk what we will of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> but if we do not take care to build up the Church of God, and encourage men to ſerious diligence about the buſineſs of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we may pleaſe our ſelves with ſuch a notion, but neither God nor man will be pleaſed with us. It's no part of our prudence nor intereſt, (I am ſure none of our duty to widen the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and weaken the intereſt of true Proteſtants, but rather to ſtudy all amicable and peaceable ways, to bring things to a better compoſure and to ſtrengthen one anothers hands againſt the common enemy. It was no pleaſing ſight to me, to ſee ſo many of our Function to ſhew ſo much zeal and heat (at our late Election of Knights for this Shire to ſerve in Parliament) for ſuch a Gentleman — who though he may be an honeſt Gentleman, and might ſerve his Country faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for ought I know; yet both you and I know that he is untried, and a younger inexperienced man, and never manifeſted that zeal and courage for the Proteſtant Religion, and the Property of the Subject (which are the two things at this time chiefly to be looked after) as his Competitor hath done. And whether he be ſufficiently ballaſted, and fortified againſt the temptations he might meet with in ſuch a ſtation, is doubtful to all, eſpecially to thoſe that conſider how the <hi>Papiſts</hi> generally fall in with him, and the charge he is at (whether at his own coſt, or others, is not mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial) to procure it. I know both you and I are expoſed to the cenſure of ſome of our Brethren for not voting with them; and reproached for being for a Fanatick or Presbyterian (though the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman is known to hold communion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as conformable as the Law requires.) And truly if ſobriety and ſeriouſneſs, and zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, and the Properties of <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> muſt denominate men for Fanaticks, and Presbyterians, we ſhall give the party ſo ſtiled, a great reputation and veneration in the minds of men, and draw contempt upon our own heads; and if we go on at this rate, we ſhall make
<hi>Ichabod</hi> to ſigh out five groans more for our Church; and inſtead of advancing the honour and reputation of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> we ſhall but bring further odium, and ſcorn and reproach upon her. I know there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy men of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe ſobriety, and ſeriouſneſs, and learning, and zeal, and moderation, doth appear to all men, which are a grace and an honour to her; but her ſpurious off-ſpring are as little pleaſed with them as with Diſſenters themſelves. And becauſe they will not rail at, and revile and reproach them that differ from them in leſſer things (though the Apoſtle ſpends a whole Chapter to teach us forbearance in theſe things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14 and our Maſter hath ſet us a contrary example, which we are commanded to follow. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21, 23. and we are called hereunto, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
3.8, 9) they reckon them no true friends to the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But I hope you and I have not ſo learned Chriſt, as to be ſhamed or frighted out of our duty, by ſuch as know not what they ſay, nor whereof they affirm We are ſatisfied in our Conſciences to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Diſcipline and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and judg the things required not
<hi>tanti</hi> to make us loſe the liberty of our Miniſtry for not conforming to them. Though we dare not ſo ſeverely cenſure others who profeſs they cannot in conſcience ſubmit to them. (And they have manifeſted the truth of their profeſſion by expoſing themſelves and families to wants and neceſſities, to ſcorns and reproaches for not doing of it.) For men may talk what they pleaſe, but <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93934:5"/>I can never believe that learned, ſober, godly, wiſe men, as (bating their differences) their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt enemies muſt confeſs many of them to be, ſhould meerly out of wilfulneſs, humour, peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and faction, keep off from theſe things, to expoſe themſelves and families to ſo many troubles and inconveniences for nothing. For how cenſorious ſoever we are againſt them, I wiſh (for the honour of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) it be a groundleſs cenſure of ſome (no enemies to the Church of <hi>England</hi> I can aſſure you) that profeſs to fear, that if ever Popery ſhould be eſtabliſhed by a Law in <hi>England</hi> (which God forbid) there would not be that number of Nonconformiſts to it, as was found at St.
<hi>Bartholomews,</hi> 1662. You and I may heartily wiſh that they ſaw things with our eyes. But whileſt men have ſuch different apprehenſions of things, and the Apoſtles rules are ſo expreſs in this caſe,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5. and again, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22, 23. we dare not but obſerve thoſe excellent rules the Apoſtle gives us in that Chapter, which we could earneſtly deſire all our Brethren would ſtudy and practice; and to as many as walk according to theſe Rules, mercy and peace ſhall be upon them, as upon the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. It's ſad to ſee how we gratifie the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and ſerve their deſigns; and when one Plot hath miſcarried, they are ſo ſucceſsfully carrying on another, and laugh in their ſleeves to ſee what fools they can make of us, to have their work done to their hands, and can fail faſter and ſafer with a ſide wind than they could with a full gale! Oh how they hug themſelves to ſee Proteſtants ſet together by the ears, and like <hi>Solomon</hi>'s fooliſh woman pull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down her houſe with her own hands. How many daily under the vizard of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> by ſpecious Pamphlets, and cunning inſinuations, would make Proteſtant diſſenters ſeem worſe than
<hi>Papiſts:</hi> So that whoſoever ſhall but offer to ſpeak of any danger from the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or move for a vigorous proſecution of the Plot, he is preſently branded for a Fanatick and oppoſed by them that pretend to be of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the moſt dangerous of the two. If the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters had been convicted of conſpiring to take away the Kings life, to ſubvert the Government, to alter the Eſtabliſhed Religion, had a ſcore of them been Executed at <hi>Tyburn</hi> upon that account, what could have been ſpoken or written more ſeverely againſt them? A ſtranger that knows: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the late Plot, taking his meaſures, and making his judgment by the Popular out-cry and clamour, which ſome that profeſs to be of the Church of <hi>England</hi> make, from the Preſs and in diſcourſe againſt them, cannot poſſibly believe otherwiſe than that
<hi>Coleman</hi> was a Presbyterian, and <hi>Whitebread, Ireland, Gavan, Harcourt,</hi> and <hi>Turner,</hi> were all ejected Miniſters at St.
<hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomews.</hi> And this courſe of theirs doth more amaze the obſerving world, becauſe Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> hath openly ſworn it at the Trial of <hi>Whitebread,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That it was the opinion of them at</hi> Paris, <hi>and St.</hi> Omers, <hi>to fling all this upon the Presbyterians, that is the death of the King. That if any thing of that nature ſhould happen, they ſhould be ready to give the firſt alarm, and give it out that it was thoſe ſtill King killing Presbyterians that had done the fact.</hi> (Like <hi>Nero</hi> of old that ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he could never have a better proſpect of it than by its own light, and then to lay it upon the Chriſtians; and as our Powder-plotters had their Proclamations ready (if their deſign had taken) to have laid it upon the Puritans.) <hi>And ſo they thought they ſhould have brought the Epiſcopal party into their company to revenge themſelves upon the Presbyterians.</hi> To which the Lord Chief Juſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, <hi>It was pretty advice indeed, to have it firſt laid on the Presbyterians, that they might get the Epiſcopal to join and cut them off, and then their own Throats ſhould be cut.</hi> For if they could get theſe old Fanaticks diſpatched out of the way, which (if we may believe them that have turned from them to us, and been the Diſcoverers of the Plot) they hate and fear as much as any of us, they would quickly find out new and freſh Fanaticks; and ſome are ready to think the name of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant would ſoon be loſt, that we muſt be all termed
<hi>Papiſts</hi> or Fanaticks. Now I muſt confeſs to you when I compare theſe things with the words and practices of ſome that would be thought white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> all the blood of my body flys into my face, (and it's either ſhame or anger or a paſſion mixt of both, that ſent it thither) to obſerve how ready they are to cloſe with this
<hi>Jeſuitical Artifice,</hi> and to turn their ſpleen and indignation upon thoſe whom notwithſtanding the more minute differences amongſt us, I dare not but own as brethren, and eſteem as zealous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants as our ſelves. In a word, if the Diſſenters be guilty of this Damnable divelliſh Plot, let 'em die for it; if innocent, why are they reviled for it? And ſhould we tempt them to think there is very little difference between guilt and innocency, that whoever is in the fault they muſt bear the blame?
<hi>Sir,</hi> it concerns us now to ſpeak, or for ever to be ſilent, and to warn our people, that they do not gratifie the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in this deſign. To conclude, Miniſters in Scripture are ſtiled <hi>Watchmen,</hi> and we had need to warn our flocks of their danger; and they are ſtiled
<hi>Fiſhers,</hi> and whileſt others fiſh for Flaces, let us fiſh for Souls. We need not envy them their Pluralities, and Dignities, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, that ſlight and ſcorn the moderation we profeſs; if God will but enable us to be diligent, and faithful in our work, and make us inſtrumental to do good to Souls, it will be a greater honour and comfort to us, when we come to die, than all their worldly advantages will be to them. Dear Brother, Farewell. Let you and I take the Apoſtles Exhortation, 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Feed the flock which is amongſt us, taking the over-ſight thereof, not by conſtraint but willingly; not for filthy lucre but of a ready mind; neither as being lords over Gods heritage, but being enſamples to the flock; and when the chief ſhepherd ſhall appear, we ſhall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away.</hi> And this is the higheſt ambition of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your unworthy Brother and Fellow-labourer. <hi>N. D.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Septemb.</hi> 22. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
